in terms of uh speech, right speech and
wrong speech.
Speech that uh we should abstain from
and speech that we should actually
cultivate. So there's this the main the main the
So there's this the main the main the
obvious one is lying
is musada
and having abandoned musada lying he is
one who abstains from lying one who
speaks the truth adhering to the truth
reliable trustworthy not a deceiver of
the world
Well, obviously you know the precepts
and then the the precepts around the
speech they just needs to be they need to be
they just needs to be they need to be
taken as standards. So say you are able
to abstain from it and you don't
compromise that standard even if um even
if your life
even if you have to experience more
nuisance and hassle and hardship on
account of you not telling lies. It's
still good to not tell lies and sustain
that standard because um it's uh well
then that that will enable you then to
start seeing the problem of speech on a
subtler level
because you know each time you speak
each time you communicate with others uh
for an unenlightened mind there are
already these implications of ownership
self view me others internally
externally communication company all of
that is maintained maintain and sustain
through speech.
That's where people often when they try
to um like even just sort of minimize
their speed, you start feeling this
pressure to just speak or say something
or chat or communicate because existence
is maintained through your
communication. But none of that will be
really um seen correctly or benefited
from unless you can even keep the basic
precepts concerning the speech. So no
lying um no no malicious tailbearing
spreading of gossip uh you have to
abstain from that but then yes then you
also get to see that and often many
sutas like when the Buddha was
addressing monks as well not just lay
people he was about don't you know don't
be engaging in frivolous speech speech
that's that's pointless which well so
which is the pointless speech well any
speech that has nothing to do with the
dhamma it's pointless speech
and uh and it should at least make a
person think cuz it sounds like oh wow
so I can't speak at all um and it's like
but why is that a problem?
Why is it a problem to be silent
if there is a need for something to be
said? Sure. But why do you also feel
this pressure to say something in
company that it has no practical value
and yet you can't help it and you have
to say it. I was like, well, that is a
problem actually psychologically that is
a problem for a mind that wants to
develop. And that's exactly the point of solitude
And that's exactly the point of solitude
and abstaining from pointless frivolous
speech unless it's connected with a dumb
or some practical purpose. You get to
see that that oh yeah, there's this
dependence on this on this pressure to
speak to communicate to say something to
touch the world on that level so to
speak to keep in touch with it so
everything is fine. And often there is
that kind of slightly anxious
uh oh just just you know just just touch
base just just keep it just okay it's
all good are you good yeah okay no it's
your idea that's all good that's what
you're trying to protect and it's all
it's it's a it's a form of control it's
a form of like okay so it's fine so then
I'm fine but the fact that you need to
do that means it's not fine and that's
probably the first thing a person that
withdraws into solitude and stops
speaking going to feel is that
insecurity and anxiety from not
communicating and speaking. But you have
to go through that.
And then when you do speak, you speak
with a purpose.
And you certainly don't speak out of
that pressure to just speak something to
say something and you know cuz I'm a bit
awkward or or or you know, you know, is
everything okay? Is everything not okay?
So all of those are your doubts, your
own hindrances and here you are acting
out of it because speech is a form of
action and it needs to be restrained. You need
and it needs to be restrained. You need
to stop, as we often say, you need to
stop acting out of unh wholesome states.
Well, doubt, insecurity, awkwardness,
all of that. Acting out of that is unh
wholesome, not immoral. But we're not
talking about now, as I said, basic
precept that make you moral or immoral.
That has to be covered. You have to be a
moral person keeping the virtue. Now if
you want to be the contemplative that
does develop its own mind on account of
you know solitude correct reflection
gradual training that we often speak
about uh yeah you realize speech is a
form of action and I keep acting out of
compulsion almost
so I need to restrain that I need to
endure it and certainly not act when I
know for sure it's rooted in uh in unh
wholesome
like not necessarily clearly anger or
something but yeah like just frivolous
it's unh wholesome from the point of
view of mind development so you could
just reflect for yourself so so why why
can't I just be silent
endure this pressure and say something
when something needs to be said but
otherwise don't compromise that criteria and you
don't compromise that criteria and you
that's that's how the Buddha encouraged
even the monks that had to kind of group
and stay in a group and live together
for one practical reason or the other at
a time to just be silent
Not like you take this blind sense of
duty vow of silence.
I will never speak. Well, now I just you
assumed another external observance.
No, you you could speak for the right
reason. That's what you need. It's not
like I can I I'll just never act again.
That's the equivalent of taking up these
I'll never speak. I'll never do any of
this. I'll never, you know, I'll never
act again. Well, that's your action.
So you cannot act but you can certainly
unlearn to act out of pressure to act
out of unh wholesome states
because it's it's a very very much
a physical thing speech that you act out
but if you can't actually u be aware of
your speech then there is no awareness
of your mind.
Exactly. So that's what I mean the
precepts the behavior that's fine you
know you have to be restrained it's not
really like
I mean a lot can be said about it but
there is really no need to it's obvious
you have to just do it with any sort of
virtue must be developed beforehand in
terms of physical behavior and action
but then it comes to speech and often
even the Buddha himself would you know
the the common eight precepts and then
he would just have those four or five
different types of speech that are
included in the basic precepts
because you realize that is like a kind
of a practical point of converging for a
mind that does want to develop. Sure,
you're abstained from you know physical
immorality by by body uh with your
actions but there is now a lot that sort
of still coming through your speech even
not in a coarse manner still keeps you
basically connected to that physical um
well the assumptions in regard to the
physical world you've been acting out
of. So if you can't if you cannot develop
So if you can't if you cannot develop
and sustain perspective in regard to
your own speech, abstain from it.
Practice as we said in in some old
talks, you know, like a like develop the
sense of a non-speaking mouth. Like
literally you are aware that you could
speak but you are not speaking and you
haven't been speaking for a while unless
there was a purpose. That becomes now an
upgrade of your virtue. In the same
sense we the Buddha would speak about um
keeping the the sense of uh like
physical restraint guarding the sense
creates this aggregate of virtue. So
basically certain behavior you haven't
been engaging for a while because you've
been keeping the precepts becomes this
solid thing that's now seen.
It's it's it's not like you're doing it.
It's what you haven't been doing for a
while. The mind recognizes oh I've been
dwelling in the state of not doing these
things. And that's when that joy on a
kind of unbroken virtue arises that
would encourage you should think about.
Well, in the same sense, you then get to
see your own non-speaking mouth that
only been speaking when there was a
purpose. No more spilling
through through this physical orifice
that you are communicating with the
world. You were no more spilling for
pointless purpose, for central purpose,
for angry purpose. And you become aware
of the fact that yes, the power of
speech has been harnessed so to speak.
You are not spilling out into the world
carelessly. You're not perverting the
order and maintaining your assumptions
of sensuality and anger and everything
else through non-speaking mouth. Mouth
that hasn't been speaking.
So the certain standard of when it's
being spoken becomes now your criteria
on account of which a samadei and sense
of joy can arise. And then what's
happening in your mind becomes even more
clearer. And then you could exactly as
the Buddha would say himself once you
start developing this sense of samadei
towards Janna it's like the mind becomes
pliable. If you want to think this you
think that if you don't you don't think
it mind listens because you stop
spilling it and perverting it and
perturbing it through physical and
verbal careless actions out of pressure
and so on. So it's a very practical
thing. It's not like hey abstain from
your speech just for some holy reason
that will become apparent later on. It's
an actual training of of of a whole
independent domain of action through
which you'll be maintaining your wrong
views and so and everything else that
that basically keeps you liable to dooka
and non-control of your own mind.
So it might feel like a bit sort of
oppressive in the beginning. I can't
speak. I can't speak. Again you you take
it on in the same sense you take the
behavior of the precepts and then it it
becomes apparent like I am dwelling in a
in a kind of
in a in a mode of being of non-spech
non-speaking mouth is my presence it's
my reality my mouth that hasn't been
speaking on account of greed aversion
delusion same like aggregate of virtue
gets upgraded into aggregate of silence
unless there is a purpose so you're not
artificial officially or externally
adhering to I must be silent to not
compromise the value of silence. No, all
I need to do is not abandon the gateway
where unh wholesome things will become a
reason for me breaking the silence and
silence remains uh unperturbed even when
I speak
and that's why after the first Janna the
second Janna is called the noble silence
when you when you quiet even your
thoughts on account of already quieting
your speech and by the way that's
another maybe side thing um people think
like in the first Janna you quiet your
thoughts and that's why your speech kind
of falls off the vat and disappears.
It's other way around. It's by subduing
fully purifying, fully developing
samadi, on account of a joy, on account
of a non-speaking mouth that hasn't been
engaging in careless speech, you quiet
your thoughts. So you quiet the speaking
mouth and your thoughts will quiet down
and your thoughts will quiet down
because each time you speak carelessly,
your thoughts spill through speech into
that world and maintain your wrong views
about it.
So you want to quiet your thoughts,
quiet your speech and it will take it as
long as it took you to quiet down your
virtue depending on the type of effort and
depending on the type of effort and
quality you invested. You know somebody
who is immoral not virtue starts keeping
the precepts it's going to be a bit hard
in the beginning and they wouldn't see
any aggregate of virtue there doing it
keeping the precepts for them and like
you know they would have to do it but if
you sustain it keeping the precepts
becomes effortless because it never was
about doing certain things it was simply
about abstain abstaining from doing
certain things and that's when that pre
precepts starts keeping you so to speak
well same abstain from spilling out into
the world through your mouth, through
careless pressure, through awkwardness,
through any other unh wholesome states,
through doubt and your silence will keep
your mind composed. That's it.
So stilling the speech, quiet is the
thoughts. Then when the thoughts are
even quieter third in the second Janna,
that's the complete silence. But you
don't have to worry about the second
Janna until you have devel until you
develop the first Janna. And you
shouldn't worry about the first Janna
until you have developed your virtue and
your speech beforehand.
But it it is it is like the first the
the speech ceases in the first Janna not
because you entered the magical state of
your thought but because you got so
imperturbed so established in an
existence of a non-speaking mouth that
has been enduring for a while and even
when it spoke it spoke on account of
things that were practical or connected
with dharma and nothing else.
So that's another reason why solitude is
necessary for that type of development.
You can't be in the world where people
constantly try to communicate and talk
to you and expect to sustain that level
of of of of nonspe speaking existence.
But you can certainly purify a great
deal of your of of all the perversions
in regard to your views about what comes
first in the world. Even in the world,
even in, you know, in day-to-day life,
just be mindful of literally of your
mouth. Be mindful of what comes out of
it. What you're saying, why you're
saying it. Don't just I'll just say it
and then for like fully give in to what
you No. Okay, I'll say it and I'll
remain mindful while I'm saying it and
I'll remain mindful after I said it
because usually it's I'm mindful. I'm
mindful as in I'm refusing to say it.
Then I can't help it. Then I decide to
say it and mindfulness disappears and I
say it. That doesn't need to happen. You
can remain mindful throughout.
Even before you decide to say it, you
should be mindful. If you decide to say
it, you should be mindful. After you
said it, you should be mindful,
which then means the the reasons for you
saying it in the first place will will
be clearer and clearer and clearer. So
yeah, practice silence
as I said not as a kind of sense of
external duty or some observance
but as a sense of no no this is this is
the gateway one of the gateways the
mouth one of the the domains of action
body speech and mind
and it will it will it will develop your
smart as well obviously there will be no
practice of right speech and and silence
and non-speaking mouth as I like to say
if your physical behavior has not
already been you know honed and tamed to
a great deal.
So
gradual train